[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
collide sends employees important timely
and relevant security recommendations
for their linux mac and windows devices
right inside slack
collide is perfect for organizations
that want to move beyond a traditional
lockdown model to one where employees
are educated about security and device
management while they're fixing
important problems
visit collide.com se radio to sign up
today
that's k-o-l-i-d-e kolide.com se radio
enter your email when prompted to
receive your free collide gift bundle
after trial activation
you can try collide with all its
features on an unlimited number of
devices for free for 14 days no credit
card required
try it out at collide.com
sc radio
hello everyone this is felina for
software engineering radio today with me
on the show james sokol james is an
engineer and leader with experience on
all parts of the web application stack
he is currently a senior staff engineer
at policy genius previously he has been
a director of engineering at colney nost
and he's also worked at bitly and
mozilla james is an active member of the
python and javascript communities and
maintains several popular open source
software projects welcome to the show
james thank you for having me it's great
to be here so the topic of today's show
is
cicd
and we're going to dive into all sorts
of aspects of that but first let's
discuss this separately because very
often we say cicd
but actually what are the parts there
what is the first part continuous
integration what does it mean according
to you
yeah continuous integration is
i think an important and
worthwhile step in and of itself but
when you're continuously integrating
you're taking small changes and bringing
them back into the sort of main code
base all the time as opposed to
something like you've got a long-lived
feature branch or a release branch
sometimes people also call it uh trunk
based development where you're just sort
of
making small changes bringing them back
and then making sure that you're running
tests builds if that's relevant on every
change so that it's all kind of just
automated and people are always working
off the most recent
functioning
hopefully version of the code so what
problem does that solve why is ci
testing or ci development process why is
that better than a feature branch or
what are the differences i think the
biggest thing that it's solved
especially in my experience is the
multiple day merge and reconciliation
process of having
multiple feature branches or teams
working on something before one release
that was just i mean i literally had
teams spend two days resolving merge
conflicts because you know there's drift
among different authors of code
different teams working on the same
thing the other thing is that it avoids
a particular even if it's small a
particular change bit rotting or
becoming unmergeable in the first place
or irrelevant you know if we've got
oh on this one branch over here we
solved this problem already so now you
don't need to bother doing it you can
avoid that sort of a rework but i think
the biggest thing is just that it's
if you're continuously
branching and merging each merge is so
much faster so much smoother that it
saves the team a lot of time overall
and are there downsides as well maybe
like merging in small changes that you
end up not using or other downsides of
the ci approach i don't know if i'd call
them downsides so much as i think there
are costs the biggest one is that you
may be merging code that's unused
in one point of view that's very safe
code but you know that's not always true
and
so you have to have some way of sort of
flagging on certain behaviors or
flagging it off if you're going to merge
something that's incomplete you have to
be sure that it's not going to be
exposed to users so there are some
mechanisms that you have to adopt and
then
there's a little bit of additional code
to write and then additional code to
remove when you're
done and integrated and you know the
whole feature is rolled out and you need
to take those flags back so i think that
there are some some costs associated
with it it's not entirely free i don't
know if i'd call them
downsides per se
sure and we will definitely dive into
those practices of how do you make sure
that you don't accidentally expose half
features to users later on but first i
also want to cover the cd part of cicd
actually cd was harder because i was
looking up a few stuff before the
episode and what is cd even mean is it
continuous delivery or continuous
deployment it seems
people don't even agree what the cd
stands for so what is your take what
does it mean and how do you define cd
i usually mean continuous delivery
although it's really worth specifying
each time it's sort of like mttr in in
that respect like which are so
continuous delivery
is
when you have this continuous
integration
pipeline or automation moving that sort
of resulting
version of the code into whatever is an
appropriate environment at least for
testing so if you're doing a mobile app
that might be publishing you know a new
built artifact if you're doing something
where you're deploying applications on
kubernetes it might be pushing a
container into a testing cluster but
taking
the artifact or the result and then
putting it someplace where
you can do something with it that's just
delivering into an environment
continuous deployment is
going a step further and saying that
every change that passes all of those
automated steps is going to production
right now
which i think is a great place to be in
if you can get there so again here the
question is what problem does cd solve
why is it good to put stuff to users as
quickly as possible
i think my favorite example is
the hotfix when you're maintaining
multiple different branches and you have
something that you need to
say you're like most of your team is
working ahead on the next release
version but it's not ready to go yet and
you discover a bug
well now you have to patch that bug and
you have to figure out if it exists in
the existing release branch or if it's
only in the new one
and it's kind of a deviation from your
normal process when you're doing cd
there's no such thing as a hotfix
because everything is optics basically
since everything is going to production
you're really optimized for making those
kind of changes quickly so
if
you have you know we have big features
that we're working on they're turned off
right now but oh we discovered a problem
it's right kind of in your your
day-to-day run of things to be able to
ship a change to it it also means for
smaller features that don't necessarily
need that they get to users faster
because they're not waiting for anything
they're not bundled up with bigger
changes and so that can mean you know a
feature gets in front of users faster
the business benefits from it sooner the
developer hasn't moved on and forgotten
about it if there are issues with it
so i can see how deploying continuously
is sort of doable if you're developing a
web app but what if you're developing a
phone app or a desktop application like
users don't want to update their apps
daily right so how does that work is cd
they're not a good fit or do you do
something differently there
so i admit that i'm not an expert in
mobile deployment but i have heard some
interesting strategies to kind of bridge
that gap because
you may want to be
shipping and testing new features faster
than you can reasonably especially on
mobile where you have app store reviews
right faster than you can reasonably
expect updates to go out
one of the things i've heard is using
webview fallback if your app is like i
don't know how to render this component
it can sort of say
but i will render this web version
instead so that you can sort of keep
testing out new features by doing cd on
the back end there's also definitely
times when you know depending on the
industry that you're working in it may
not be appropriate if people need to
certify releases before they can roll
them out like government or health care
insurance sometimes you know that can be
a reason not to do cd certainly not to
do continuous deployment of
versions of you know software to
customers
you know there are always going to be
situations in which it's not the best
fit i think getting that kind of like
continuous delivery
aspect of it like let's always be
testing this and be ready to ship a
version of it
is
a good middle ground in those situations
so that we can say like hey again we
have a critical bug we need to upload
the logging library we can do that right
away but yeah there are definitely some
times when continuous deployment is
going to be more difficult especially if
you do need users to to make updates
yeah that makes total sense
so let's dive into tools that are needed
so okay you have convinced me of the
benefits of cicd
i also want this for my app now what do
i do like what type of tools do i need
to have a good workflow
so tend to think about this in terms of
what i call the triforce of deployment
if you've ever played the zelda games
the triforce is these three components
of
wisdom
power and courage
tooling i think mostly falls into sort
of the the power the capabilities that
you you have but
it also kind of can lean into the the
wisdom side so
one i think you do need a way to turn
things on and off you need to be able to
shift code that's not complete and have
that be okay code that's even broken in
the sense that it it may not work at all
so feature flags are kind of the typical
way that we talk about that or feature
toggles i'm not really familiar with
this is there a difference between a
feature flag and feature toggle or are
they just synonyms
i think they're just synonyms i don't
think there's a meaningful i think there
are different kinds of them you know
something that's like long-lived and you
may want to shut off for operational
reasons versus something that's part of
a release but yeah i think mostly just
synonyms another really important tool
is you need a way to automate your build
process so you need some kind of you
know automated task runner whether it's
something like jenkins
if you're going relatively old school or
using github actions or any of the
number of
sort of ci tools that exist now
need version control something that you
know makes branching easy hopefully that
one is
at this point
relatively common but
you know it might not be so you
mentioned jenkins or git of actions sci
tools so what does such a ci tool do
largely what a ci tool is responsible
for is executing a series of steps and
so sometimes they're called pipelines
because they you know move from one step
to another along a defined progression
the sort of first step is usually some
kind of like all right let's let's
gather the artifact let's figure out or
let's gather the inputs to the artifact
figure out the things that we need to
execute like let's run tests let's run
linting if that's a thing that is
relevant
security analysis might be relevant and
then producing sort of a build artifact
of some sort whether it's a an ec2 ami
or a container or you know an apk if
it's an android app but they're
responsible for that sort of
orchestration of you know here's five or
ten steps or whatever it is
let me execute each one of those in
sequence usually in sequence sometimes
things are parallelizable and
bail out if some part of it fails but
producing the the end result the end of
the pipe
and you also mentioned testing as part
of the pipeline so what is the role of
testing there
i think of testing as part of a
broader spectrum of sort of confidence
and that kind of falls into the triforce
of courage you need confidence that what
you're about to ship is okay and testing
is kind of your your first line of
defense you know if we can do automated
unit tests and then you know integration
tests on top of that that gives us more
confidence that the code we're about to
write is or the code we're about to ship
is correct or is at least
incorrect in an acceptable way so
you know leveraging that sort of
certainty and
confidence that you get from having
those tests pass and then you know
confidence kind of continues along the
spectrum there are certain things that
you need to know that you can't test
like
i need to know that my production
application is connected to my
production database no unit test will
ever tell me that so that kind of takes
you forward into monitoring and learning
which i think all part of the same sort
of spectrum of
how do i know it's working
yeah maybe we should dive into the topic
of monitoring because now we're
discussing like the happy bet right so
there's a there's a branch and this is a
pull request or something is accepted
and now the tests run and now everything
is deployed hooray
but what if i accidentally deployed
something where all my tests were
passing but
something else happens i get issues
downtime whatever so is this
rolling back manually or automatically
is that also part considered part of the
cicd workflow that if i can quickly
deploy i should also be able to quickly
roll back if it's necessary yes and i
think that that's one of the strengths
is that if i introduce a small change
and it goes to production and it causes
something to go wrong right and
you know that fun thing of every every
bug that made it to production made it
through the test suite so they all did
that i know which change introduced that
and i can roll that back quickly or you
know if it's uh if i want to do a git
revert and roll forward i can do that
quickly but having the ability to ship a
change very fast is
it's what cd is set up to do and it's
particularly valuable in that situation
if you are doing something like
containers or
other binary builds maybe if you're you
know working in go or another sort of
compiled language and you can
just ship the artifact that you had just
previously shipped you can save all of
that kind of build and test time and say
this this one was a known good one let's
just get it back out there
usually most of the tools are able to
sort of redo just the last step
of the deployment if not it might take a
little longer to rerun the tests but so
if i have decided what tools to use how
do i run the tools so you mentioned
jenkins and github actions is this stuff
that is typically used in the cloud like
github actions is running on someone
else's machine or would you advise
having a dedicated machine in your own
infrastructure there maybe this depends
on what situation you're in what would
your advice there i mean i think with
almost everything the answer is going to
be it depends to some extent but there
are a number of really good cloud tools
and if i'm not interested in maintaining
that infrastructure myself and i'm i'm
really not anymore then you know i see
unless i have some sort of regulatory or
compliance or
i have a large enough team with the
staff to dedicate to maintaining those
tools then i would rather use something
that somebody else is going to
operationalize and take care of so
those are the ones that i would look to
first if i can that does mean
there's usually some level of setup of
you know if i'm running something in my
own infrastructure there might be fewer
permission things that i need to worry
about in terms of you know pushing new
code into a running environment of mine
but i think it's probably a worthwhile
trade-off but for most teams to say like
i'm just going to use somebody who knows
what they're doing here so something
that you know connects into whatever
your source controls either
web hooks so you can sort of trigger
these on push or
can periodically pull source control for
for changes and kick off new builds that
way but
yeah i mean
always build versus buy as a trade-off
it depends for every company but i think
there's a lot of good options out there
to buy and get yourself set up yeah so i
think what you're saying is unless
expressing reasons because you're not
allowed to just using cloud tools is a
good easy start
absolutely so let's talk about
configuration of search workflows so i
want to
say okay unit tests and then some
integration tests maybe a stress test or
a performance test these are the things
i want to do before i'm going to run my
ci cd
what do i do what are typical solutions
there do i script this in a language do
i click this together with a web builder
what are some of the solutions and maybe
your advice or some on different options
there
so most of the cloud tools use yaml as
sort of a configuration format you can
define they all have
variations on a similar structure of
here's the steps that i want to run and
then in each step you usually have quite
a lot of freedom to sort of define
what is executing so you know whether
it's go test or npm test or
or you want to say actually this is a
little bit complicated i need to set
some environment variables so
i'm going to wrap this in a shell script
and then execute that shell script but
for the most part when you're looking at
configuring one of these tools it's
going to be a big yaml file you know the
fewer steps the shorter it'll be but
specifying you know these are the
environments that i need these are the
environment variables these are the
inputs and this is where i download
everything that i you know pull in my
dependencies or whatever the other build
steps might be for that particular
language or environment and then you
know if you're doing containers there's
obviously docker files almost always
docker files that are part of that as
well but usually it starts with the ammo
and what about dependency management so
suppose one of my features or something
that used to live in a feature flag but
is now already integrated this
needs a new version of one of the
libraries that we are dependent on where
do i manage that is that part of this
workflow as well
most of the languages that i've gotten
to work in recently have some concept of
dependency management in a lock file so
that you can get these reproducible
builds that's particularly valuable for
the transient dependencies or transitive
dependencies right if you don't want
something changing downstream without
your knowledge of it so usually that's
something that's managed locally by the
developer and then sort of checked in as
a change to that lock file or to the
upstream dependency file and then there
are some caveats to this but your ci
setup if you're building something with
dependencies is usually going to pull
down whatever the sort of specified
dependency versions are so
each time you build that particular
change you should be getting the same
versions
there are
sometimes when people are particularly
security conscious especially in you
know ecosystems lots and lots of little
libraries like javascript
they'll use an intermediate proxy
something that they have to sort of
approve new versions of code to go into
from the public registry
that one is you know not about for
everybody it depends on sort of your
security needs and the trade-offs you
want to make but for the most part you
know it's managing lock files is more of
a
beginning of the pipeline flow and then
the pipeline should be
respecting whatever is in your
dependency lists and log files
okay so let's talk about the
practicalities of this so we know now
what tools to use but how do i do this
like what type of knowledge is needed to
properly set the
in in the good old days maybe we had a
system administrator that did such
things right that deployed or that made
installers for different versions what
skills do we need to get such a process
going
well it depends a little bit on which
tools you choose to use and on which
you know what type of environment you're
deploying into so
if you're
building containers to run on like an
eks or on google cloud's you know
kubernetes engine you're going to need
some people who are familiar with
creating containers and getting them up
and running in kubernetes different
cloud tools have different levels of
support there but
you know usually you do need somebody
who's familiar with whichever cloud
you're using and can help sort of
administer the permissions and the
deployment
targets and environments a lot of the
goal of this is sort of in line with the
devops philosophy of moving the
responsibility towards the
software engineers who are
writing the code so
the actual pipeline steps sort of once
you have
the
okay we can produce an artifact and we
can put it someplace and then run it
mostly you then want to hand off sort of
responsibility for all the steps in
front of that to
the team working on the software that
lets them kind of
say i know what we need to do to build
this we need to make this change here
that might be a point of collaboration
between you know teams that are managing
more of the infrastructure and teams
like security that want certain things
to happen but hopefully you're able to
sort of push a lot of that into the
individual teams and have them take
responsibility for it
that doesn't absolve you from needing to
manage the actual cloud infrastructure
or
you know physical infrastructure if
that's what you're doing
so then now you're also saying all team
members should
be able to change the workflow or run
the workflow or is there in a team still
one dedicated person that maybe manages
this workflow and other people just use
it like how do you divide the tasks
there typically what do you think is
best
i think it depends on
the number of sort of
teams contributing to the same space so
if i were to be in a more micro service
environment where you know the blast
radius of making a change is limited to
a single service or a single team then
i'm more likely to say the team should
own it if i'm in an environment that's
more of a monolith it's more of a
or a mono repo in that case i might lean
more towards we're going to move
responsibility towards dedicated you
know team especially in a larger group i
know for a long time the way that
facebook deployed was they built one
single gigantic binary for most of the
service
that's the sort of thing where i
probably want like a release manager or
release engineers who are dedicated to
doing that
while you know if i've got 10 teams and
10 or 15 services and they can really
only mess things up for themselves that
badly
then
rather than having a release engineer on
every team or even a core group of them
sort of like yeah they can learn what
they're doing they can take care of it
so some people also say that that ci cd
is not necessarily about tools but it's
more about having a certain mindset like
always be delivering always be deploying
would you agree with that and would you
say like what defines this mindset
absolutely i think there's
one that always be shipping aspect of it
like let's get this in front of people
right let's
there's no test quite like putting it in
production
so
like let's get it out there as fast as
we can whether that is you know to learn
something to be certain about it or just
because hey you know this is a bug fix
let's get it to people faster let's not
wait so i think that's a big part of it
i also think there is this sort of
i don't want to call it
like heroic but this idea that every
piece of code you write is going to
production
there's no net there's no qa that's
going to catch a mistake that you made
there's no
user acceptance testing or if you've
really automated this process nobody's
gonna
besides the person who wrote it and the
people code reviewing it
nobody else is looking at it before it
goes live so
there's a certain responsibility i think
that that comes with that and that i've
seen is hard to replicate it's hard to
tell people
think about your code as if it's going
to production right now if it's not but
then on you know that first monday when
you say okay it's going now you can kind
of see the way people react like oh
okay
i need to be a little bit more thorough
or more careful yeah so i think what
you're saying is that the idea that
you're always shipping sort of creates
an urgency
creates a sense of responsibility
because it's actually going out there
soon and not in three months or in six
months ah we can deal with this later
absolutely so how do we translate always
be shipping to concrete actions i mean
always be shipping is a bit like eat
healthy and exercise more right clearly
this is a good idea
but now what do i do day to day how do i
get this mindset in my team because it
is so tempting to say oh you know i'm in
this branch oh just a little bit of this
oh but you know what's also related to
this feature this and then
and still i'm in a feature range like in
my own in my own open source project
where i'm working i have a few of these
very long-lived pull requests where a
contributor is sort of out there i'm
like okay so so how do i get them to
adopt this always be shipping mindset
how do we get there practically so i've
seen teams open source projects are a
little bit more of a challenge because
you you know have less cohesion but
what i've seen teams typically do is
kind of go through a couple of steps one
is
okay we're doing feature branches we're
doing these big you know if you're
starting there some teams
start a little further along this path
but
and every time we do this it's a big
deal we don't deploy very often it's
risky we have these big merges
and one of the first steps i think that
can really help
break that mindset is okay we're going
to do this every week or every other
week we're going to move to sort of a
scheduled model away from a
when it's ready model and that means
that everything that's in there is going
to go out on you know on thursday it's
going to go to staging and the next
thursday it's going to go to production
and that's our qa window now i think the
biggest thing that that does is it
encourages because you're shipping
you're doing deployments more frequently
it encourages you to automate those and
then feel more
once you start automating pieces of it
you feel more comfortable with it like
okay it's probably not going to break it
didn't break last time and that you know
keeps building up that confidence
yeah and i guess also this exposes
issues right because if you only deploy
once every year then it's like oh you
know what do we have to do again whereas
if you do this more frequently then you
have to figure out how to do stuff
automatically because you cannot think
oh i have to set this directory to this
and that because it's just it doesn't
scale if you have to do this daily or
weekly yeah if you rely on a single
person you might say
hey you know they're on vacation this
week so we're gonna just shift the
deploy to next week but if you are doing
it weekly then you can't rely on that
person because they need to be able to
go on vacation yeah so yeah there are
all sorts of things that i think shake
out and there's the good xkcd comic
about you know how often do you have to
do something to make automating it
worthwhile
well a good way to force that is to do
it more often
time scale db from your friends at time
scale is the leading open source
relational database with support for
time series data time series data is
time stamped so you can measure how a
system is changing time series data is
relentless and requires a database like
time scale db with speed and petabyte
scale
time scale db is the postgres you know
and love with time series superpowers
familiarity flexibility speed that's
time scale
visit them today at tsdb.co
se radio
that's tsdb.co
and are there like intermediate steps so
imagine we're still in a team that has
this feature branch's mentality and it's
hard to go from that to yes but we
deploy three times a day so
what do you do then like do you break a
feature open features and you have
people do tiny feature branches or do
you say no this gradual approach is not
good you should just say hey
as a team we decide and we are not doing
feature branches we're now doing
quickly deployment what is a strategy to
to move a team towards the cicd way
well i think that sort of intermediate
step of something like a scheduled like
you know release train model is what we
used to call it mozilla which was our
you know we promote to different
environments on a periodic schedule i
think that can be a good middle ground i
do think that at that point you need to
introduce the concept of the feature
flag
because that's the point in order to
make that switch you have to have some
way of saying if it's not done by
thursday when we go to staging that's
okay
it's turned off it's behind this flag so
we're able to
ship even though it's incomplete i think
that that's kind of the first big
mindset shift right as being like okay
with shipping and complete code and that
does require some tool support but once
you've got that sort of
routine down i think if you're saying
like we're going to start every two
weeks
then you can shorten it then you can
maybe shorten it to every day
and the change set gets smaller and
smaller and then at some point you do
kind of have to just rip the band-aid
off and say all right the next change is
going to production
so you mentioned that this mindset shift
also interacts with the tools how is
that like what tools help or what tools
hurt make this shift
feature flags are an interesting
they're kind of the one of the keys to
unlocking cd and
and even ci and they
come with their own kind of burden at
the same time you need them but now you
also have to manage them
right you have to worry about deleting
flags when you're done you have to
decide who's going to put the flag in in
the first place if multiple people are
contributing to a feature and i've
definitely seen a lot of teams kind of
struggle with the
well when's the right time should this
be behind a flag do i need to flag every
change it's like well
no you can probably make that css fix
without flagging it
it's probably alright
but you know there's a big fuzzy gray
area in between
obviously yes and obviously no so
i've definitely seen that be a stumbling
block that
not so much the use of the flag i think
for the most part a feature flag is an
if statement in the actual code but the
when do i use a flag can be a big sort
of learning steep learning curve an
opportunity but
you know i think intuition is the
result of experience and once you do it
a few times and sort of get used to it
you start to develop some of that
but of course listening to experts can
be shortcuts to intuition so
do you have maybe sort of a grasp of you
just mentioned like oh a css fix
probably fine without a flag like
when do i know if my the complexity of
my code is going over the i need a flag
threshold like are there decisions to be
made
yeah so i think that one thing if
depending on your sort of like product
and team environment if you're doing
something that's an experiment that's
something that's probably going to be
behind a flag you know the difference
between a b testing and feature flags is
really the branding of the tool that
you're using
so
hopefully if you're in an environment
where you're doing that then anything
that's an experiment is sort of
automatically a feature flag
anything where it's going to take a
couple of steps to finish
or it could reasonably take a couple of
steps to finish is a spot where it might
be a good opportunity to flag sometimes
you can write code that's just
unaccessible and unused and
you know get away without doing the flag
and that can help but
you know when it comes to
something where all right we are
changing the way that this works then
that's and it's going to take you know a
handful of days then that's something
where you probably want to flag it
or anything that's just sort of
risky and unknown like if you don't
necessarily have a performance
profile for something yet a lot of the
feature flag tools
most of them can do some kind of
percentage roll out so you might want to
say like i don't know how this is going
to work in production so we're going to
turn it on for 10 of people just to sort
of see how it scales and what sort of
load it generates so that's another good
reason why you might want to flag
something just to have that kind of
control over it and then do you
typically leave the flags in forever
like imagine at one point you're happy
and then 100 of users has been using
this feature
i don't know for three weeks or whatever
good granularity is do you leave them
there so you could always toggle if
needed or at one point the feature is
just a core feature or would you say no
flags stay there forever
if they stay there forever it's gonna
start to become kind of a combinatorical
nightmare so i think a big piece of
using flags and one of those costs
that's associated with them is
you have to go back and clean them up a
lot of teams that i've known have
had a practice of as soon as we create
you know the first ticket to
start a feature that is going to be
behind a flag we also create a ticket to
remove it um is there like a timeline
you say we make this ticket and it has a
deadline in
always three months or does this depend
on the type of feature it depends on the
type of feature i'm not sure that i've
seen a team with like a hard and fast
rule on that deadline especially if it
is something a little riskier and you
might go back and forth on it you know
i've
part of the point of feature flags is to
be able to turn it off if something goes
wrong which if that happens might extend
your timeline i think it's more about
what is kind of the total load of flags
your team can be maintaining at once
than the lifetime of a particular flag
so if it's to this point where you know
you've got a team of five people and
30 or 40 flags in your application
that's just by itself introducing a lot
of complexity and a lot of code that
might be unused so
starting to remove them is is
going to be more important as they kind
of pile up i think more so than
strictly speaking the time
that said you know i've also seen people
introduce a flag in one working on a
particular ticket ship something turn
the flag on and then as part of the same
ticket remove the flag just because they
wanted that kind of safety and often
with stuff that small you know the flag
might live for hours
yeah that makes total sense so let's
talk about data because most
applications nowadays have
data in a database
sometimes a new feature might require
migrating data like adding a certain
column in a database table in the front
end
might mean that existing users that did
not yet have this field object
need to be initialized or get a default
value or maybe generate a value from
already existing data
how does that figure into the equation
like do i ha
first integrate just the migration of
the data and then the front end or this
is this then maybe a bigger package how
do we deal with features that require
changes to existing user data one thing
i think is that these problems can be
very fun
i really enjoy
zero downtime deployments and zero
downtime changes so i think the first
thing is to ask yourself honestly if
that's necessary because sometimes it's
not right if you have a very geographic
user base you might be able to say we're
going to do this offline migration we're
going to take 20 minutes in the middle
of the night we're just going to do it
if you have services that are facing uh
like a call center or an operations team
that you know has specific hours
sometimes it's okay even a minute of
downtime might be totally acceptable so
i think the first thing is to like
really say is it going to be worth it
but let's say that it is worth it
because this is a fun problem so
there are a couple of approaches that
i've seen for
this sort of migration i think the the
one that i tend toward is
try the new path if the new path doesn't
work
fall back to pulling data from the old
path and migrating it
on demand that's going to introduce
some additional latency for people the
first time they go through because
there's a little bit more to do
but it prefers the new data if it's
available so you know as
the more frequent users or the first
people will start putting load into the
new system
depending on what the feature is you may
want to double write data if there are
changes into both old and new versions
if that's applicable
you know if it's a new feature there may
not be anything to put into the old one
but at least for a while until you're
you're confident in the new system and
then you can also kind of look at
if you've instrumented this you can look
at what percentage of our you know
requests are falling through to the old
path and that's a fun graph to watch so
i've usually seen this as kind of a
three-step process that i would love to
have a name for if if anybody knows one
of introduce this new path with fallback
to the old path eventually you're
probably going to have to do something
for the people who haven't logged in if
you're doing that kind of online
migration and do a backfill
that can usually be done slower and in
batches
and then
go and remove the migration code and now
you're just on a new path
yeah so then maybe you have like two
sort of flags like there's a flag for we
have released this feature and there's a
flag for have we actually migrated
everyone to the new
data structure yeah and maybe you know
one of those flags could be dependent on
the other there are
some tools that let you do that where
like flag a can only be on if flag b is
already on for a particular user or you
know one of them might be user based and
the other one might not because you're
doing this on the back end
so this is interesting this this flag a
can only be only flag b is already on
where do you manage that is this
somewhere in your code base as you said
the flag is just an if statement or is
it this additional layer
in the library or in the cicd
platforms so one of the really
interesting things to me about feature
flags is that
the goal of a feature flag tool is to
separate the conditions under which
something is true from the code that
cares about whether it's true so in the
code where i'm writing the feature all i
should care about is is this flag on or
not that's the question that i'm asking
the future flag
library usually it might be a client for
some kind of server it might be
a library built into the code that's
managed someplace else then has certain
sets of conditions that make it true so
the the easiest condition is it's on for
everybody or it's off for everybody you
know then you can get into it's on for
authenticated users or it's on for
people from this ip address block or
it's on for
people on
ios but not on android you know whatever
kind of like set of criteria or set of
features the tool supports so there are
tools like launch darkly that support a
lot of things out of the box but allow
you to write custom rules often you will
have to initialize a client like this
with some kind of user context
but the idea and the real power of it
comes from being able to separate those
conditions and those triggers from the
places that care about the result and
then those conditions are also described
in something like emo file or does this
live in a a function that you inherit
that depends a little bit on which tool
you you choose to use if you want
something like
feature flags as a service and there are
a handful or
even some open source versions that it's
a feature flag service that you run
internally then that is really state of
the feature flag application that you
can
configure one of the real powerful
things there is that it's because it's
application state it's not a code change
to turn something on or off so you could
even have you know a product manager go
and say i'm going to hit the release
button because it's 9 am on tuesday and
that's when we said we were going to
turn it on but by separating it out from
actual
source control that sort of gives you
that ability to say oh we deployed it
and there's a problem we were talking
about earlier i'm going to turn the
flyback off yeah without deploying again
just keep running as it is you just turn
a boolean out somewhere
so let's talk about programming
languages you already sort of hinted at
there are some differences between
different programming languages because
for example if you compile to a binary
it's very easy to go back to your
previous version if you still have the
binary somewhere on the shelf so to say
you can just grab the yesterday's binary
and put it back back out there also some
programming languages of course might
have longer compilation times so are
there
important differences in ci cd tools or
practices between
java or python or typescript or would
you say mo that's all by and large the
same
i think
all of them have some
commonality for example all of them
should be able to run a clean build from
scratch which might be the slowest
version
you might need different levels of
i would say start with what your
performance targets are and then work
backward to see sort of what you need to
do to achieve that so
for example
you know something where you're pulling
in a lot of dependencies from whether
it's like python or
javascript or ruby from a third party
that step might take time so you might
want to cache those like most caches i
would say
don't do it right off the bat do it if
you find out that you need to but
and different languages are going to
have different performance you know
realistically different sort of
performance characteristics of their
package ecosystems like you said
compilation times
some languages support incremental
compilation you know if you're caching
or keeping around the sort of build
environment and you're using something
like go or like c you know with a
well-constructed make file that can do
that kind of incremental compilation
then that might be faster and might be
something you want to enable
with i think always the capability to be
able to say like no do it from scratch
clean the build environment start over
just as a baseline but i like to work
backwards from what am i trying to
achieve can i get this build to be under
five minutes if you're running certain
linters the answer is probably no so
sort of five minutes is this a realistic
goal or an important goal or does that
depend also on what you're building
i think it's realistic i think the
important goal
is how distracted am i going to be as a
developer when i hit the merge button
and then let this process start am i
going to be
sitting there for half an hour trying to
remember that i'm waiting for this to
happen the shorter you can make that
feedback loop the better i think five
minutes is it definitely doable a number
of the backend services at frontend
services actually we've gotten our sort
of deploy time from merge to production
to be under six minutes our reports only
go to the tenth of an hour so i think
they're faster than that
so i do think it's a reasonable for
decently large applications to hit that
target but yeah it's really about
attention for me because one of the
goals here is to you know we talked
about the example of like oh i wrote
this and then three months later it got
deployed like i don't remember what that
was
i have no idea what i was doing so if i
can stay kind of in that headspace of
like i'm shipping this i'm watching the
monitors i'm watching logs oh that's a
new error i can see how that's connected
to the code i just wrote to kind of keep
that context the longer your build time
the harder it's going to be for people
to do that
yeah and also i guess the longer the
build time is the harder it is to do it
often because if i have to wait for half
an hour i'll do something else in
between i'll come back i don't want to
do that two times a day that's that's
annoying whereas if just a click of a
button it doesn't really matter if it is
a single environment that is a hard
limit on how many times even multiple
people can deploy per day right if it
takes half an hour you've got
48 deploys
so you mentioned that there are
definitely commonalities between
different programming languages but
maybe there are also differences so
what are some differences
well a big one is you know whether or
not it produces a binary by itself and
that's something that you can move
around or if
you know if you're doing something like
containers that might not be as
important because you can treat the
container as an artifact as a binary but
if you're say you're doing you know
python environments shipping those
to servers can be
tricky
if you're not using containers so one of
the things that i've seen is you know
each production server that this is
running on has to go through some of the
build steps by itself just because
replicating that environment requires it
i think that's a good reason to use or
move towards something like containers
if you can that said you know adopting
something like kubernetes is a lot and
it may not be for everybody whereas you
know if you're moving a go by an area or
a java
jar around that might be a lot simpler
because it's just like okay here's the
file it'll run
we you know cross compiled or do
whatever we needed to do
so i think that that's a big
big difference like whether or not you
have at the end of this process a binary
artifact
there's also you know if you're dealing
with front-end languages
what deployment means might be entirely
different i need to get static files
someplace i need them to be on a cdn
where browsers can access them i might
need to point something somewhere at a
new
url to download those static files
that can also sort of really change your
your final steps like maybe deployed
into an environment means that css and
javascript bundle is in a bucket now
which is a very different process from
kicking off new containers so
there are very much sort of results
towards the end of the pipeline that
depend on the languages and the
environment that you're building into
and i guess maybe also a bit on the
architecture because if you have a mono
repo everything's in one place then
the flags in the process just lives
there for this thing whereas imagine if
you have a certain microservices
then
maybe i need to deploy
three or four services redeploy with a
certain flag and maybe the other ones
are just they remain as is they're not
impacted by that that change so i guess
architecture also plays a role there
right absolutely i used to maintain for
a long time waffle the feature flag tool
for django applications and i'm no
longer sort of the day-to-day maintainer
of that sometimes you have to move on
from open source projects but one of the
reasons that i kind of
moved away from it was that it's not an
effective way to manage those sort of
microservices and that's a case where
you want flag state to be effectively a
cross-service global right like every
service should read the same state for
that flag so
that's when something like a feature
flag as a service either
sas product or something that you're
running internally is really important
so
yeah you might exactly have that kind of
situation where
hey three things need to pay attention
to this at the same time in a mono repo
maybe i just deploy all of them at the
same time i make the change in one
commit
right across all of the services where
all of the components of the code
whereas in microservices it's like nope
this has actually got to be spaced out
now there's no way that i can coordinate
that all of these will change at exactly
the same moment although again sometimes
one of the things i've had to learn is
that it's okay for there to be
you know it might be fine for there to
be 30 seconds of downtime in the middle
of the night or something it's all right
i don't like making changes in the
middle of the night though i like making
changes when i'm awake so
i'll attempt to yeah i think there's
research that shows that these deploys
on friday afternoon or friday evening
are always more
likely to introduce bugs just because
people are tired and they they want to
have the thing over with so it is maybe
not a good idea to deploy when it's late
night for you um right when it's late
night for your customers it's fine but
if it's late night for you then you just
might not be in your best mind at that
point right in time
yeah i think it's all about are you
gonna be there to support it for long
that you feel confident right so if i'm
working till eight on a friday i'll
deploy at six i don't care but if i'm
trying to leave for the weekend it can
wait that'll go on monday it's fine
so i think that's most of what i wanted
to ask you today is there anything
important any any life lessons about
cicd that we've missed any advice you
want to share with our audience
well one thing that i think is
been a real like learning opportunity or
thing that i've gotten to experience
several times is that a lot of these
things are improvements even if you
don't get all the way to
continuous delivery or deployment right
if you have the ability if you think
that you're doing trunk based deployment
and you think that that branch is ready
to go at any given point even if you're
not actually doing it
there's a lot of practices that you've
adopted that are gonna sort of help
the other thing that we haven't really
talked about but i think is a very
important aspect to this what i would
call the triforce of wisdom component is
having insight into the system you know
we touched a little bit on monitoring
but
this is a whole range of you know do i
have observability tools in place you
know am i whether that's
metrics or logs or spans or doing
request traces or whatever the
appropriate thing for this environment
is can i see how the system is running
can anybody file an issue if they see a
problem right like
anybody in the company anybody in the
team should be able to sort of raise a
hand and say hey i noticed this or hey a
customer emailed me about this
we have a customer forum you know i
think etsy has like a seller forum that
they watch for quality issues just to
keep that feedback loop tight i think
that that's a really important aspect of
doing this successfully as well is
having that that insight into
is it working right are there things
that i'm unaware of that other people
might be and can they surface that yeah
and if people want to know more about
that specific topic we just recently had
a show on analytics that would show 496.
so if you do want to dive into that side
of monitoring and understanding what's
going on in the application then
definitely we will put a
link to the show 496 in the show notes
talking about the show knows is there
anything from your site that we can add
to the show notes like where can we
follow
you your work any links we should add to
the notes
well my
website is just jamesfocal.com
and from there you can find twitter
github my blog which
is called coffeeonthekeyboard.com which
i would consider changing but it's been
around for so long but there are links
to it so it is cute yeah it's got it's
got a brand to it i suppose
but yeah everything is sort of linked
for my website and i have a draft that i
need to re
that did not survive blog back end
transition that i need to rewrite but i
want to publish this week about the
triforce model because i've talked about
it a few times and i figured
yeah if you have that post if that's
live when we publish this episode we
should definitely ask that to the show
notes if it's not i'm gonna be very
disappointed in myself well this is
maybe a good deadline for you to get it
finished in a few weeks i think so okay
i guess that's it thank you so much for
being on the show with us today james
thank you for having me it's been uh
great talking to you about this
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening